UTKARSH SONI

Tempe, AZ

https://usoni1.github.io \((+1 4804343856) \(\) usoni1@asu.edu

SUMMARY

A Ph.D. student with research interests in human aware Artificial intelligence. Specifically, I work on personalizing the interaction between an AI agent and the user. This involves personalizing the explanation the agent provides for its actions, and allowing a user to specify their preferences for some sequential decision making task (like reinforcement learning).

EDUCATION

Arizona State University

Aug 2018 - Present

Doctor of Philosophy (PhD)

Current GPA: 4/4

Expected Graduation: May, 2024

Arizona State University

Major: Computer Science

Aug 2016 - June 2018

Master of Science, Computer Science (MS CS)

GPA: 4/4

Major: Computer Science

International Institute of Information Technology - Gwalior

August 2011 - April 2016

Bachelor and Master of Technology.

CGPA: 8.36/10

Major: Information Technology

COURSES TAKEN

Artificial Intelligence, Statistical Machine Learning, Topics in Reinforcement Learning, Data Mining, Data Visualisation, Fundamentals of Statistical Learning, Social Media Mining, Distributed Databases and others.

TECHNICAL STRENGTHS

Python, R, C, C++, MySQL, Java Languages

Web Technologies D3.js, JavaScript, JSON, NodeJS, HTML, CSS, Flask

Machine Learning Frameworks Scikit-Learn, Tensorflow, PyTorch, Pandas

Tools Tableau, Gephi, MATLAB, Git

RESEARCH

- Soni. U., Sreedharan, S., Kambhampati, S. Not all users are the same: Providing personalized explanations for sequential decision making problems. Accepted in IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems IROS 2021; (link).
- Sreedharan, S., Soni, U., Verma, M., Srivastava, S., Kambhampati, S. Bridging the Gap: Providing Post-Hoc Symbolic Explanations for Sequential Decision-Making Problems with Inscrutable Representations. Accepted in ICLR 2022; (link).
- Mishra, A., Soni, U., Huang, J., Bryan, C. Why? Why not? When? Visual Explanations of Agent Behavior in Reinforcement Learning. Accepted in Pacific Vis 2022; (link).
- Soni, U., Lu, Y., Hansen, B., Purchase, H. C., Kobourov, S., Maciejewski, R. The perception of graph properties in graph layouts. Accepted in EuroVis 2018.; (link).
- Chen, H., Soni, U., Lu, Y., Huroyan, V., Maciejewski, R., Kobourov, S. Same stats, different graphs: Exploring the space of graphs in terms of graph properties. IEEE transactions on visualization and computer graphics TVCG 2019.; (link).

- Gopalakrishnan, S., **Soni, U.,** Thai, T., Lymperopoulos, P., Scheutz, M., Kambhampati, S. (2021). Integrating Planning, Execution and Monitoring in the presence of Open World Novelties: Case Study of an Open World Monopoly Solver. *Workshop on Integrated Planning, Acting, and Execution ICAPS 2021.*; (link).
- Gopalakrishnan, S., **Soni, U.,** Kambhampati, S. Feature-directed Active Learning for Learning User Preferences. *International Workshop of Explainable AI Planning ICAPS 2019*; (link).

WORK EXPERIENCE

ASU Yochan Lab - Research Assistant

Jan 2019 - Present

Advisor: Dr. Subbarao Kambhampati

- Developed a technique for providing personalized explanations to the user for robot's decisions in sequential decision making problems. The technique first learns all the possible user-types, and then frames the interaction between the human and the robot as a partially observable markov decision process with user type as latent variable.
- Developed a technique that can compute explanations for decisions taken by a reinforcement learning agent by creating a local symbolic approximation of the task.
- Currently working on an interface that helps build a symbolic middle layer between a human and a deep learning based reinforcement learning agent to allow a human to communicate their preferences for the agent's policy.

ASU Vader Lab - Research Assistant

Jan 2017 - April 2018

Advisor: Dr. Ross Maciejewski and Dr. Shade Shutters

- Conducted large scale user studies to model how humans perceive different network properties (like graph density or clusters) depending on the automatic graph layout algorithm that is used. In particular, I empirically showed that the difference between two graph property value that the human would notice is proportional to the value of the property.
- Worked on a urban employment tool with technologies like Python Flask, JavaScript and D3. Created multiple websites for government decisions makers that help them analyze multiple aspects of employment data in their region.

ASU- Graduate Teaching Assistant

Aug 2018 - Dec 2018

• Teaching assistant for a graduate level data visualization course.